<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="BookId" lang="en">
<bookinfo>
    <title>MonALISA Client User Guide</title>
<!--    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Iosif</firstname>
        <surname>Legrand</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <address>
            <email>Iosif.Legrand@cern.ch</email>
          </address>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
-->    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>California Institute of Technology</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="general-features">
    <title>General Features</title>
    <para>
      The global monitoring service client allows to discover all the
      active services, and display real-time global views for
      connectivity and traffic as well as the usage and load of the
      monitored entities.
    </para>
    <para>
      It allows to access the configuration of any site and display
      real-time or historical values for any monitored parameter in
      the system.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using the WebStart technology, it can be started from anywhere,
      with just a single click in a browser window.
    </para>
    <sect1 id="requirements">
      <title>Requirements</title>
      <para>
	In order to run the MonALISA Client, the following program
	tools must be installed:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Java 2 Runtime Environment, version 1.4.2. You can
	      download it from <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">
	      http://java.sun.com/j2se/</ulink>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Java Web Start. You can get the latest version form
	      <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart/">
	      http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart/</ulink>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Java3D, for the 3D Globe Panel. The MonALISA client can
	      work without this panel, but, for a better experience,
	      it is reccommended that you have it. The Java3D must be
	      installed for the JVM that it is going to be used with
	      the client, and it is available for the following platforms:
	      <variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Windows and Solaris</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/3D/">
		      http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/3D/</ulink></para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Linux</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><ulink url="http://www.blackdown.org/java-linux/java2-status/java-3d-status.html">
		      http://www.blackdown.org/java-linux/java2-status/java-3d-status.html</ulink></para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		  <term>Mac OS X 10.3.1 or later</term>
		  <listitem>
		    <para><ulink url="http://www.apple.com/downloads/macosx/apple/java3dandjavaadvancedimagingupdate.html">
		      http://www.apple.com/downloads/macosx/apple/java3dandjavaadvancedimagingupdate.html</ulink></para>
		  </listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	      </variablelist>
	      <note>
		<para>
		  If you reinstall the JVM, even in the same
		  directory, you should also reinstall the Java3D
		  package!
		</para>
	      </note>
	      <note>
		<para>
		  If you have more JVMs installed on your machine, when
		  you click on the MonALISA jnlp (Web Start) file to
		  start the client using a browser, make sure that the
		  JVM used by the browser has the Java3D package installed!
		</para>
	      </note>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="main-window" xreflabel="Main Window">
      <title>Main Window</title>
      <para>
	The main menu of the application has the following items:
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>File</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Contains only the Exit command.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Discovery</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This menu can be used to change the discovery 
		process of the monitored entities. There are two
		parts regarding this process:
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      the Lookup Services hosts - used in the Jini
		      discovery of the Proxy Services. These are fixed
		      for each type of client and should not be changed.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      the available Groups - used in the Jini
		      discovery of the groups to which the monitored
		      entities are subscribed. Usually, the MonALISA
		      Client already comes with all available groups
		      added so adding a new one is necessary only in
		      special situations.
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Groups</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This menu can be used to switch on/off the currently
		active groups. Usually, different types of monitored
		entities are grouped in separate groups. You can use
		this menu to add/eliminate (un)necessary entities from
		the client views.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Security</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This can be used to specify a keystore and a password
		that allows controlling the entities. More on this in
		the <xref linkend="farm-properties-win"/> section.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>Help</term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This brings a window with some nice screenshots.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	On the left side of the main window, there is a list of
	labelled icons with the active panels. These can operate in
	two modes:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      single view - each panel is displayed in the main
	      window. When other icon is clicked, the current panel is
	      replaced by the new one.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      multi view - the current panel remains in the main
	      window. Clicking other icon opens the respective panel
	      in a new window. Clicking the icon again closes that
	      window. Clicking the "Multi-view" icon closes all opened
	      windows.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <sect2 id="globe-panel">
	<title>Globe Panel</title>
	<para>
	  The monitored entities are displayed on a 3D Globe that can
	  be manipulated with the mouse. You can left-click on an
	  entity to open the corresponding property window (See <xref
	  linkend="farm-properties-win"/> section for more details.)
	  You can zoom in/out using the mouse wheel. Right-clicking
	  and dragging rotates the globe. Middle-clicking and dragging
	  moves the globe. These operations can also be performed with
	  the left button by selecting one of the buttons above the
	  panel (Translate, Rotate, Zoom).
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/vrvs-globe-pan.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/vrvs-globe-pan.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Globe Panel</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Globe Panel
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
<!--	<figure>
	  <title>Globe Panel</title>
	  <graphic fileref="images/vrvs-globe-pan1.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
	</figure>
-->	<para>
	  If the mouse is moved over a node or arrow of a link, a
	  short text is displayed, showing status information.  The
	  information shown on the nodes and links can be changed
	  using other buttons above the panel.
	</para>
	<para>
	  For a description of the values shown for each node and link
	  please see the client specific details in <xref linkend="farm-client"/>
	  and <xref linkend="vrvs-client"/> sections.
	</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="wmap-panel">
	<title>Wold Map Panel</title>
	<para>
	  The monitored entities are displayed on a flat world
	  map. Left-clicking a node brings the corresponding property
	  window. Using mouse wheel you can incrementally zoom in/out
	  the respective area of the map. You can also zoom in by
	  selecting a region with the right mouse
	  button. Right-clicking the map restores the original zoom
	  state.
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/vrvs-wmap-pan.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/vrvs-wmap-pan.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>WMap Panel</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The World Map Panel
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
<!--	<figure>
	  <title>World Map Panel</title>
	  <graphic fileref="images/vrvs-wmap-pan1.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
	</figure>
-->	<para>
	  If the mouse is moved over a node, after one second a
	  tooltip will be displayed, showing information about the
	  node. The information in the node can be changed by the
	  buttons and combo boxes on top of the panel.
	</para>
	<para>
	  For a description of the values shown for each node and link
	  please see the client specific details in <xref linkend="farm-client"/>
	  and <xref linkend="vrvs-client"/> sections.
	</para>
      </sect2> 
      <sect2 id="gmap-panel">
	<title>Graph Panel</title>
	<para>
	  This view represents the entities in a graph-like form. The
	  nodes can be moved with the middle mouse
	  button. Left-clicking a node brings up the corresponding
	  property window. Right-clicking a node makes the selected
	  node a "source" node. Starting from that point the client
	  will compute a path towards the other reachable nodes.
	  There are several layout modes for the nodes, modes that can
	  be changed selecting one of the buttons above the graph
	  panel. If a tree can be computed, the "Tree layout" modes
	  will be available.
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/vrvs-gmap-pan.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/vrvs-gmap-pan.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Graph Panel</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Graph Panel
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
<!--	<figure>
	  <title>Graph Panel</title>
	  <graphic fileref="images/vrvs-gmap-pan1.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
	</figure>
-->	<para>
	  The information shown for each node can be changed with the
	  combo-boxes above the graphical area of the panel.
	</para>
	<para>
	  For a description of the values shown for each node and link
	  please see the client specific details in <xref linkend="farm-client"/>
	  and <xref linkend="vrvs-client"/> sections.
	</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="tab-panel">
	<title>Table Panel</title>
	<para>
	  This panel shows a table with various details for each
	  entity. 
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/farm-table-pan.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/farm-table-pan.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Table Panel</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Table Panel
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
<!--	<figure>
	  <title>Table Panel</title>
	  <graphic fileref="images/farm-table-pan1.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
	</figure>
-->	<para>
	  This table can be sorted by clicking the caption of table's
	  columns.
	</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="histo-panel">
	<title>Histogram Panels</title>
	<para>
	  In these panels a bar chart with different values is drawn
	  for all entities. If there are more values for each entity,
	  the histogram can be drawn as a stacked bar.
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/farm-histo-load-pan.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/farm-hist-load-pan.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Load Histogram Panel</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Load Histogram Panel
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>

<!--	<figure>
	  <title>Histogram Panel</title>
	  <graphic fileref="images/farm-histo-load-pan1.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
	</figure>
-->	<para>
	  Right-clicking on the panel brings up a menu from where you
	  can change the colors, the type of the chart (simple,
	  stacked), appearance (plain or 3D), orientation etc. You can
	  also save the chart in a <filename>.png</filename> file.
	</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="farm-properties-win" xreflabel="Node Properties Window">
	<title>Node Properties Window</title>
	<para>
	  Left-click on a node in Globe, Graph or World Map views,
	  brings up a window that shows Node's local time, IP address,
	  MonALISA version that runs there and various site
	  information. However, the most important information is a
	  tree view containing the monitored clusters and nodes. For
	  each node and cluster on the right side is an available
	  parameters view. On the lower-right part the modules list
	  that gather that information is shown.
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/farm-rcframe-plots.eps" format="EPS"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/farm-rcframe-plots.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Node Properties Window</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The Node's Properties Window
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
<!--	<figure>
	  <title>Node Properties</title>
	  <graphic fileref="images/farm-rcframe-plots1.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
	</figure>
-->	<para>
	  You can select a node, or a cluster from the tree view and
	  some parameters from the right panel and click on History or
	  Realtime Plot buttons. A plot window will pop-up and soon
	  the requested data will be drawn.
	</para>
	<para>
	  You can right-click on the graphs to change different
	  properties (line width, graph background, axis labels etc.),
	  print or save the graph in a file. Using the options in the
	  window's menu, you can change the appearance (3d/2d,
	  stacked/simple, direction), manage the displayed graph sets
	  (add, remove, change colors) and analyze sets (integrate,
	  compute median value etc.).
	</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="farm-client" xreflabel="Farm Client">
    <title>Farm Client</title>
    <para>
      We will present here only the particular features of the
      MonALISA Farm Client. For a larger view, please see the <xref
      linkend="main-window"/> section.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each node represents a computing farm and is drawn as a pie
      chart. The values to be shown in the chart can be selected from
      the combo-box that appears above the graphical part of the panels.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are two types of links in this client:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    ping links - ranging from red to yellow, represent the
	    quality of the links as computed by the ABPing module
	    (taking into account the round trip time, packet loss, and
	    jitter) for each peer of a node.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    wan links - ranging from light blue to dark blue,
	    represent the traffic on the WAN links.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Based on the ping links values, in the Graph panel you can
      right-click a farm to compute a path from that node to all
      reachable nodes. The client will use the Dijkstra algorithm and
      the selected links will be drawn in blue. Note that this will
      form a tree and the tree layout modes will be available.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="vrvs-client" xreflabel="VRVS Client">
    <title>VRVS Client</title>
    <para>
      We will present here only the particular features of the
      MonALISA Farm Client. For a larger view, please see the <xref
      linkend="main-window"/> section.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each node is drawn in a specific color, representing the
      selected value in the combo-box on top of the graphic panel.
      For example, if in the combo-box the selected value is that of
      the Total Traffic, the application will compute a minimum and
      maximum value for all VRVS reflectors. Beside the combo box, a
      color scale will be drawn, representing lower traffic with a
      light blue and higher traffic with a darker blue. All the nodes
      on the Globe, World Map and Graph Panels will be coloured with a
      blue nuance according to their own traffic.
    </para>
    <para>
      When there is no data coming from the reflector for the
      currently selected item in the combo box, the node will be drawn
      in pink in the panels. If there is no data from a reflector (no
      information about ping or peer links, no data about the number
      of clients, virtual rooms, traffic or load), the node will be
      painted in red. However, this doesn't mean that the node is down
      - you may be able to open node's properties window and plot
      different parameters from other clusters.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are two types of links between the reflectors:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    peer links - ranging from red to green - represent the
	    quality of the links between the reflectors, as it is
	    measured by the reflector software. You can choose from
	    the Peer links combo-box the value to be displayed
	    (mediated for 2, 12 or 24 hours). 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    ping links - ranging from red to yellow, represent the
	    quality of the links as computed by the ABPing module
	    (taking into account the round trip time, packet loss, and
	    jitter) for each peer of a node.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    mst links - represent the links that should be used as
	    peer links for the reflectors. These are dynamically
	    computed by the client based on the values of the ping
	    links and the status of the reflectors.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      You can hide or show the links using the checkboxes above the
      graphical area of the panels.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that both peer links and mst links connect the nodes in a
      tree structure. You can use each of those in the Graph Panel to
      generate various tree layouts.
    </para>
  </chapter>
</book>
